# **Vladimir Ulyantsev**

I am a PhD in computer science, associate professor and a head of Computer Technologies Laboratory (ITMO University), which now consists of 7 groups & 130 members. I have managed and participated in more than 10 R&D projects, co-authored more than 45 research papers, supervised more than 25 students (including ICPC champions).

Research interests: discrete optimization, machine learning, generative design, bioinformatics

**Selected skills**: research unit & project management, faculty work, funds attraction **Personal values**: independence, ambition, logic, responsibility, social well-being

Hobbies: swimming, skiing, surfing, singing, texas holdem

#### Career overview

Born in 1990 in St. Petersburg, Russia. I have been keen on math and programming since early childhood. Started studying computer science and programming in ITMO University in 2007, also started my career with developing and organizing programming contests. I've developed more than 100 problems, coaching teams for ICPC championships in Russia, USA, Uzbekistan.

In 2010 started a research career on developing evolutionary and Boolean satisfiability (SAT) based methods for solving NP-hard problems. Defended a PhD thesis on automata synthesis using SAT and Constraint Satifaction Problem (CSP) solvers in 2015. In 2014 also started working in the area of bioinformatics, developing tools for metagenomic WGS analysis in collaboration with Research and Clinical Center of Physical-Chemical Medicine, Moscow.

In parallel with a research career, established as a leader and supervisor. Since 2012 participated in grant fundraising and project supervision. After defending a PhD thesis, in 2016 was appointed as the head of a joint ITMO-JetBrains Research lab (12 members). Since 2017 became the head of the Computer Technologies Lab, facilitated the expansion of the Lab from 10 members to 7 groups of a total of 130 members.

## Work

### **ITMO University, Computer Technologies Laboratory**

lab head Jul 2017–now

decision making, strategic planning, resource management, fundraising, collaborations establishment

#### ITMO University, Information Technologies and Programming Faculty

associate professor Sep 2016–now

supervising bachelor, master & PhD students, leading projects on computer science, machine learning & bioinformatics

#### JetBrains Research

head of optimization problems in software engineering group

Jul 2016–Feb 2022

#### ITMO University, Computer Technologies Laboratory

head of discrete optimization group Sep 2013–Jul 2019

**ITMO University, Computer Technologies Laboratory** 

researcher Apr 2010–Dec 2015

ITMO University, Information Technologies and Programming Faculty

programming contests development & organization Mar 2008–Mar 2010

**Education** 

ITMO University Saint Petersburg, Russia

PhD in Computer Science

2013-2015

Information Technologies and Programming Faculty, Computer Technologies Department

Topic: Finite-state machine synthesis using SAT and CSP solvers

ITMO University Saint Petersburg, Russia

Master's degree in Applied Mathematics and Informatics

2011-2013

Information Technologies and Programming Faculty, Computer Technologies Department

ITMO University Saint Petersburg, Russia

Bachelor's degree in Applied Mathematics and Informatics

2007-2011

Information Technologies and Programming Faculty, Computer Technologies Department

**Software** 

MetaFast https://github.com/ctlab/metafast

developer, algorithms designer, team leader

2014-now

METAgenome FAST analysis toolkit for feature extraction and calculating a number of statistics of metagenome sequences

MetaCherchant https://github.com/ctlab/metacherchant

team leader, algorithms designer

2016-now

tool for analysing genomic environment of a nucleotide sequence within a metagenome  $% \left( 1\right) =\left( 1\right) \left( 1$ 

RECAST https://github.com/ctlab/RECAST

team leader, algorithms designer

2018-now

pipeline for analysing metagenome time series and distinguish which reads of one metagenome sample are found in other samples

GADMA https://github.com/ctlab/GADMA

supervisor for optimization algorithms

2017-n

tool for automatic inference of the joint demographic history of multiple populations from the genetic data

**EFSM-tools** https://github.com/ctlab/EFSM-tools

developer, algorithms designer, team leader

2010-2019

toolset for finite-state machine (FSM) synthesis

Selected funded projects

RSCF grant https://rscf.ru/en/project/21-71-00051/

principal investigator

2021-2023

Feature extraction for de Bruijn graphs of groups of metagenomic samples and whole-genome metagenome datasets classification using machine learning

RSCF grant https://rscf.ru/en/project/18-71-00150/

principal investigator

2018-2020

Evolution strategies for hard SAT-instances decomposition with application to cryptographic functions inversion

**RFBR A-grant** 18-07-01285

principal investigator

2018-2020

Machine learning methods for synthesizing finite-state models of control systems with regard of temporal properties and timestamps based on propositional encoding

#### Joint ITMO-Aalto project

14.587.21.0032

senior researcher 2018–2020

Development of methods, tools and technologies for design, verification and testing of reliable cyber-physical systems

**RFBR PhD grant** 14-07-31337

PhD student 2014–2015

Automated reliable software synthesis from test examples and temporal constraints using automata-based programming

# Notable supervised students

2021: Artem Ivanov (MS)

2020: Ilya Zakirzyanov (PhD), Artem Pavlenko (MS), Darya Zvyagintseva (BS)

2019: Artem Ivanov (BS), Roman Melnikov (BS)

2018: Ekaterina Noskova (MS), Artem Pavleko (BS)

2017: Ilya Zakirzyanov (MS), Vyacheslav Moklev (BS), Ilya Kachalsky (BS)

2016: Artem Vasilyev (MS)

2015: Ilya Zakirzyanov (BS), Mikhail Melnik (BS)

## **Selected bioinformatics papers**

- 1. Olekhnovich E, Ivanov A, Ulyantsev V, Ilina E. Separation of donor and recipient microbial diversity allows determination of taxonomic and functional features of gut microbiota Restructuring following Fecal Transplantation. **mSystems**, 2021. 10.1128/mSystems.00811-21
- 2. Noskova E, Ulyantsev V, Koepfli K-P, O'Brien S, Dobrynin P. GADMA: Genetic Algorithm for inferring Demographic history of Multiple populations from Allele frequency spectrum data. **GigaScience**, 2020. 10.1093/gigascience/giaa005
- 3. *Zhernakova D et al.* Genome-wide sequence analyses of ethnic populations across Russia. **Genomics**, 2020. 10.1016/j.ygeno.2019.03.007
- 4. Olekhnovich E, Vasilyev A, Ulyantsev V, Kostryukova E, Tyakht A. MetaCherchant: analyzing genomic context of antibiotic resistance genes in gut microbiota. **Bioinformatics**, 2018. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btx681
- Dubinkina V, Ischenko D, Ulyantsev V, Tyakht A, Alexeev D. Assessment of k-mer spectrum applicability for metagenomic dissimilarity analysis BMC bioinformatics, 2016. 10.1186/s12859-015-0875-7
- Ulyantsev V, Kazakov S, Dubinkina V, Tyakht A, Alexeev D. MetaFast: fast reference-free graph-based comparison of shotgun metagenomic data. Bioinformatics, 2016. 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw312

# **Selected computer science papers**

- 1. Zvyagintseva D, Sigurdsson H, Kozin V, Iorsh I, Shelykh I, Ulyantsev V, Kyriienko O. Machine learning of phase transitions in nonlinear polariton lattices. **Communications Physics**, 2022. 10.1038/s42005-021-00755-5
- Semenov A, Chivilikhin D, Pavlenko A, Otpuschennikov I, Ulyantsev V, Ignatiev A. Evaluating the hardness of SAT instances using evolutionary optimization algorithms. CP 2021. 10.4230/LIPIcs.CP.2021.47
- 3. *Chivilikhin D, Zakirzyanov I, Ulyantsev V.* BeBoSy: Behavior Examples meet Bounded Synthesis. **IEEE Access**, 2021. 10.1109/ACCESS.2021.3057823
- 4. Zakirzyanov I, Morgado A, Ignatiev A, Ulyantsev V, Marques-Silva J. Efficient Symmetry Breaking for SAT-Based Minimum DFA Inference. LATA 2019. 10.1007/978-3-030-13435-8\_12
- Pavlenko A, Buzdalov M, Ulyantsev V. Fitness comparison by statistical testing in construction of SAT-based guess-and-determine cryptographic attacks. GECCO 2019. 10.1145/3321707.3321847
- Chivilikhin D, Ulyantsev V, Shalyto A, Vyatkin V. Function block finite-state model identification using SAT and CSP solvers. IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics, 2019. 10.1109/TII.2019.2891614
- 7. *Ulyantsev V, Buzhinsky I, Shalyto A.* Exact finite-state machine identification from scenarios and temporal properties. **International Journal on Software Tools for Technology Transfer**, 2018. 10.1007/s10009-016-0442-1
- 8. Zakirzyanov I, Shalyto A, Ulyantsev V. Finding all minimum-size DFA consistent with given examples: SAT-based approach. **SEFM 2017**. 10.1007/978-3-319-74781-1\_9
- 9. *Ulyantsev V, Zakirzyanov I, Shalyto A.* BFS-based symmetry breaking predicates for DFA identification. **LATA 2015**. 10.1007/978-3-319-15579-1\_48

## **Achievements & activities**

- Programme committee member of AAAI'2021, AINL '2016 '2017 and SNR'2017
- In 2020 together with Artem Ivanov won both tracks of PMI Metagenomics Diagnosis for Inflammatory Bowel Disease Challenge (MEDIC) (https://www.pmiscience.com/whats-new/ winners-of-sbv-improver-machine-learning-diagnostic-challenge-announced)
- Delivered scientific and popular science lectures on various open stages, a small collection available here: https://ulyantsev.com/talks/
- In 2019 took part in a standup show, joking on scientific mindset
- Starting 2018 actively serving in ITMO University' councils, doing my best to evolve internal university policies
- In 2009 have been coaching ICPC team of A.F. Mozhaysky's Military-Space Academy, that was the only time their team managed to get to semifinal